Mary Chrystie Papers, 1833-1841: Finding Aid
Cotsen Children's Library
- Storybooks and Journals, 1831-1837; 7.0 items
  - Unbound writings by Frances Few Chrystie, 1831-1833; 20.0 pages 16 x 19.4 cm Unbound group of 20 pages (10 fols.) sewn together (not including 4 additional pages that have been cut out of the gathering). (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Unbound group of 20 pages (10 fols.) sewn together (not including 4 additional pages that have been cut out of the gathering). Writings by Mary Chrystie's mother, Frances Few Chrystie, including ones written on February 15 and 16, 1831, and others written between January 4-31, 1832; February 1-4, 1832; January 4-28, 1833; and February 19-26, 1833. The writings include accounts of Mary's education and lessons, her piety, and her daily activities. Parts of the text are written in dialogue form between Mary ("M") and her mother ("F").
- Diary of Mary Chrystie, 1837-1840; 294.0 pages 16.5 x 20.8 cm 3/4 bound, marbled boards; 4 blank pages at front, with an additional 4 blank pages at rear; 294 ruled pages. (Volume 3)
  294 ruled pages, 221 of them with inscriptions, unpaged. Written on front pastedown: numbers in a column, 2 small drawings of a house, a floorplan(?), and the outline of Mary Chrystie's hand; pinned to the first page: four printed stanzas beginning "And thou, my loving child..." from the poem "A Mother's Thoughts Amidst her Children" by Mrs. Charles Tinsley. Above this is written "Mary Chrystie / from / her / Father on / Christmas 1837". Drawn on first recto of the first blank rear fol. is a detailed study of the upper story and eaves of a house; on verso of second blank fol. at rear is an outline of Mary's foot. Written on rear pastedown: column of dates (Monday 14 to Wednesday 14, followed by "How I will jump when I can say this day is Wednesday 14 October 1840". Written next to S 27: "Here I am now"); a few odd words; another floorplan and a few squiggles; verso of last ruled folio bears what looks to be an expense ledger begun on 1 January 1839, with entries for cash and candy. Mary wrote consistently in this journal up to page 221 (fol. 111). Odd pages thereafter bear writing--after some blank pages Mary writes "I wonder where I will be when I get here / I am now at the Priory longing for home". Laid in the MS are 2 pieces of colored scrap paper (greyish purple and dark pink); sewn into the pages in various locations are feathers and fur belonging to Mary's pet birds, other birds, and dogs. This is the journal Mary remarks upon in one of her letters as having received from her father for Christmas in 1837. She wrote in it while in school at Pelham Priory, 1837-1840.
  Not arranged according to any arrangement scheme.